Weymouth, Mass. Old South Church records, 1723-1905.
Congregational Library & Archives
Weymouth, Mass. Old South Church records, 1723-1905.
RG5273
Congregational Library & Archives
0.72 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
The Second Church in Weymouth, also known as the South Church, was gathered in 1723 with James Bayley ordained as the first minister. The first meeting house was constructed in 1722 and the second in 1785. The ordination of a Universalist minister in 1834 resulted in a rift in the church membership with the orthodox members eventually forming the Union Church in 1842. The third meeting house was constructed in 1854. In 1892 the Second Church was incorporated as the Old South Church in Weymouth. In 1918, the Old South Church and Union Church merged to form the Old South Union Church. This collection includes meeting minutes, committee reports, vital records, financial records, and ministerial records.
Old South Union Church (Weymouth, Mass.)
Second Church (Weymouth, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Permananetly loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives, 2014 and 2015, by the Old South Union Church in Weymouth; recieved in two batches: accessions 2014-120 and 2015-2.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Custodial History
The Church records, 1723-1818, the Parish records, 1723-1811, and the Parish records, 1812-1868 were rebound and repaired by the Northeast Document Conservation Center in 1977.
Historical Note
With the resignation of Rev. Peter Thatcher, pastor of the First Church in Weymouth, in 1718, the residents of South Weymouth decided to create a new church closer to their community as the travel to North Weymouth was difficult to impossible depending on the season. In 1722, the South Weymouth community built the first meeting house and in 1723 the Second Church, also known as the South Church, was gathered following a successful petition to the General Court of Massachusetts. Reverend James Bayley was ordained as the first minister of the Second Church. The second meeting house was constructed in 1785 and in 1788 a silver bell for the church was procured and placed in the belfry. In 1819, a Sunday school was organized in part by the efforts of Rev. William Tyler.
Following the dismissal of Rev. Charles Warren in 1834, a parish committee was formed to search for a new minister. This committee chose Rev. Sylvanus Cobb, a Universalist minister, and the result was an almost immediate split in the church, with the orthodox majority leaving. In 1838, Rev. Wales Lewis was ordained as a compromise minister; however there was no major reconciliation between the two parts of the parish. In 1842 the orthodox members formed as the Union Church, making the split permanent.
In 1854 the third and final meeting house was constructed. A Holbrook organ was installed into the church in 1858. This was later replaced by a Hastings organ in 1903. In 1865, as the story goes, the silver bell cracked while being tolled for the death of Abraham Lincoln. The ball was recast as a new bell shortly there-after. Between 1871 and 1872, the Union Church built a new church building almost directly across the street from the Second Church. In 1873 a vestry was added to the church building. On May 2, 1892, the Second Church was incorporated as the Old South Church of Weymouth.
After years of efforts from members of both churches, the Old South Church and Union Church merged and became the Old South Union Church on November 18, 1918. The Union Church building became the Parish House. The building was torn down in 1963 and the space converted into a parking lot. In 1948, the Old South Union Church voted to become a member of the United Church of Christ, and has remained a part of that denomination since. In 1957, the third meeting house underwent extensive renovations which greatly expanded the space available within the church. The church building was rededicated in 1963.
The Old South Union Church in Weymouth continues to serve the South Weymouth community today.
Scope and Contents
The records within this collection document the administrative history of the church and the vital records of its members. This collection includes meeting minutes, committee reports, baptismal records, marriage records, membership lists, financial records, and ministerial records.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged by topic, first, and then by chronological order by the first date.
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Bibliography
Old South Union Congregational Church: 1723-1948. Old South Union Church: Weymouth, 1948. 17.11.1 W54.78 OldSUC
Robinson, Myrtle E. & Kevitt, Chester B. Ed. Two-Hundred-Fiftieth Anniversary: Old South Union Church. Old South Union Church: Weymouth, 1973. 17.11.1 W54.78 OldSUC
Baptismal records.; Church discipline.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers -- Massachusetts -- Waymouth.; Deacons -- Congregational churches.; Installation (clergy).; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Ordination.; Pews and pew rights.; Old South Church (Weymouth, Mass.); Old South Union Church (Weymouth, Mass.); Second Church (Weymouth, Mass.); Union Church (Weymouth, Mass.); Weymouth (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Church records, 1723 1818; 1723-1818 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  Digital Copies
  These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
  Scope and Contents
  This volume of church records includes the original covenant and first signers, records of choices for deacon, baptismal records, communion records, marriage records, membership lists, records of dismission, meeting minutes, and records of votes.
- Church records, 1818 1886; 1818-1886 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  This volume of church records includes a membership list from 1819, records of the ordination of Rev. William Tyler, records of admittance and dismission, baptismal records, meeting minutes, records of censure, records relating to the choice of deacons, ordination records, and council minutes.
- Parish records, 1723 1811; 1723-1811 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  This volume of parish records includes meeting minutes, including records related to ministerial pay, and committee reports.
- Parish records, 1812 1868; 1812-1868 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  This volume of parish records contains warrants for meetings, meeting minutes, committee reports, including a report of the building committee, pew rental charges and records of pew sales, membership certificates, and membership lists.
- Committee report, 1773 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  This is a report of a committee regarding the building of a school house.
  Separated Materials
  This report was separated from the Parish records, 1723-1811.
- Judge's report, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  This report from a judge indicates that the signature of James Beal on a deed was authentic.
- Minister's history, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  This note was removed from the Parish records, 1723-1811.
- Financial records, 1774 1826; 1774-1826 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  This account book contains extensive records on the expenditures and income of the church.
- Financial records, 1826 1873; 1826-1873 (Box 3)
  This account book contains detailed financial records related to the expenditures of the church and its various sources of income. The account book provides great details on who was paid and for what services. The book provides further details related to donations and various subscription drives.
- Financial fragment, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  This fragment was removed from the Parish records, 1812-1868.